## **David Fournier**

Email: dave.fournier@gmail.com Phone: +44 790 536 9182

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/david-fournier-ba8b1595 Location: London

## **Summary**

IT Professional with more than 20 years of experience, and more than 12 years as a senior manager in IT Operations. Prior to that I worked in development, support, and customer facing roles in consultancy, pre-sales and training. This range of experience allows me to understand the pressures from all sides of the business and form working consensuses. I have been entrusted with responsibility and oversight for many large systems, projects and contracts and have vindicated that trust with stability and success. I am extremely detail oriented, having designed and executed solutions for complex systems, but remain adaptable to changing priorities. I am excellent at relationship management both within the business and with external vendors. The teams I manage buy into a shared philosophy and goals that drive them to achieve. Extremely hard working and a conscientious team player, I am looking for a role where I can drive operational and technical excellence throughout the company.

# **Skills and Technology**

I have the following skills and have worked with the technologies listed.

#### **IT Management**

IT Department Management	Budget Management	Policy Design and	
of Multiple Teams	CapEx and OpEx	Implementation	
ITIL Service Management	Agile Methodologies	Audit Management	
Software Licensing	High Availability	Disaster Recovery	
Information Security	Identity Management	Capacity Planning	
System Architecture	Cloud Architecture	Hybrid Architecture	
Network Architecture	Hardware Architecture	Storage Architecture	

#### DevOps

<u> </u>				
Cloud Computing	CI/CD Pipelines	Containers and Orchestration		
(AWS	(Jenkins, GitFlow, GitLabFlow,	(Docker, Swarm and		
also GCP & Azure)	GitOps)	Kubernetes)		
Infrastructure as Code	Automation	Source Control		
(Terraform)	(Ansible and Jenkins)	(Git, Bitbucket, GitHub, GitLab)		
Secret Management	Monitoring	Logging		
(Hashicorp Vault)	(Prometheus, NewRelic)	(ELK)		

#### Database

Oracle 7.3 - 12c	SQL Server 6.5 - 2019	MongoDB (NoSQL)	
SQL Server Always On	Oracle RAC and Data Guard	Mirroring and Replication	
Data Migration	Data Warehousing	Data Retention (Archiving)	

#### System Administration

Ubuntu	Red Hat Enterprise Linux	Bash	
CDN (Cloudflare)	Proxies (NGINX)	Application Servers (Tomcat)	
SIEM Integration	Virtualisation (ESX)	Networking (DNS and CIDR)	

# **Employment History**

#### Rank Interactive

London, UK

March 2020 to October 2022

Rank Interactive is a leading international digital gaming company. As a subsidiary of Rank Group plc, Rank Interactive provides the online gaming platform for many brands including Mecca Bingo and Grosvenor Casino.

#### **Head of Platform and Infrastructure**

May 2021 to October 2022

I was promoted to the role of Head of Platform and Infrastructure and made responsible for the resilience and performance of the RIDE platform. This is the shared platform which supports Rank Interactive's proprietary brands.

When appointed, we were migrating the Rank Group's largest brand by volume to the platform, Mecca Bingo. I was given oversight of the DevOps, Database and Infrastructure and Network teams who looked after all aspects of the platform. These functions had previously operated independently, so I had to create and implement a shared working model. This included creating a 24/7 on call rota for out of hours support. This involved negotiating coverage and financials with the business, documenting the solution, points of contact and calendar and implementing it with the teams.

The company Stride had been purchased by the Rank group for its gaming platform. As a result it was very immature and sized for much smaller brands. Working closely with the Test and Delivery functions, I ensured the platform was appropriately sized for several orders of magnitude more traffic. The platform components included Cloudflare CDN, Firewalls, Load Balancing, Proxies, Swarm clusters, AWS services, Databases and all of the associated DNS, networking and hardware. The upgrade involved adding servers and replacing firewalls, upgrading SQL Server and utilising Always On Availability Groups and upgrading application clusters to add additional nodes.

In addition, I worked with Rank Group Security teams to ensure the platform was secured. This entailed creating and enforcing policies in compliance with our UK Gambling Commision licence and external auditors. I supported Security through several audits a year with minimal impact once I had implemented policies.

Concurrently, we were building the next version of the platform and associated technologies. This was to be based on EKS in AWS using GitLab for CI/CD. In addition I was working with the Data teams on their ETL processes in relation to our platform. The goal of this was to shift historic data out of our OLTP databases, both to improve performance and enable a migration from on premise to RDS.

In September of 2022, we completed migrating the Rank Group brands to our proprietary RIDE platform with the migration of Grosvenor Casino. This was the completion of several years of work, increasing agility and reducing cost by removing reliance on third party suppliers. Having completed the migration, the business made the decision to offshore the London based technical functions.

- Formed the Platform and Infrastructure department from autonomously managed teams.
- Scaled the proprietary gaming platform for tens of thousands of players per hour.
- Wrote and implemented policies in compliance with ITIL v4 and ISO 20000 standards.
- Worked with Security on external and UK Gambling Commission audits.
- Worked with technical teams on the design of the next generation AWS based platform.
- Completed a comparative review and promoted GitLab solution for CI/CD.
- Worked with the Data team on near real time ETL processes and data retention.
- Managed out of hours incidents providing leadership, communication and technical guidance.
- Vendor management for data centres, hardware, software and managed services.
- Cost optimisation for AWS and On Premise spend.

#### **DevOps Manager**

March 2020 to April 2021

I was hired as DevOps Manager by the CTO of Stride Gaming which had been purchased by the Rank Group for their proprietary platform. However, the platform was completely unmanaged, with no suitable test environments and developers having full access to Production. My remit was to quantify the platform and take ownership of it. This included the build and release processes, which had been done manually at that point. To do this, I drove a GitOps solution using Bitbucket and Jenkins.

I was very hands on initially as there was a lack of discipline and knowledge. Within months, my team had built Development and Performance environments and rebuilt and migrated to new Staging and Production environments. This was done using scripts to automate standardised build processes, while enforcing access controls and patch management. We also built a containerised NGINX solution.

As I had been successfully managing the DevOps function, I was asked to take control of the DBA function as well. This involved building the team, quantifying assets and ensuring it was manageable and managed. Again, as the company had been immature, the first task was to secure access to the system without affecting Production or testing, as the developers had direct access to the databases.

- Quantified chaotic platform and scripted it such that new environments could be created.
- Built/rebuilt and migrated to new environments for Production and test.
- Produced NGINX and Jenkins containers for proxying and as a GitOps release mechanism.
- Oversaw the creation of the DBA team and took ownership of database strategy and security.

## **Inspired Entertainment Inc.**

London, UK

January 2007 to January 2020

Inspired Entertainment Inc. is a global provider of gambling products and managed services for licensed premises and online gaming. In my time with the company I served many roles, the details of which are below.

#### **DevOps Manager**

January 2017 to January 2020

I was promoted to the role of DevOps Manager with the broad remit of modernising Technical Operations methodologies and tooling. I decided on an automation strategy using Ansible. We fully automated an online gaming product to perform upgrades/downgrades and build development and test systems guickly.

Subsequently I managed the operations side of a multi-million pound project in which we completely refactored the company's main product, responsible for more than 60% of revenue. In addition to build automation, this involved upgrading all base software, e.g. RHEL, Oracle, MSSQL, Apache, Tomcat. Liaising with the relevant technical experts, I architected and documented the solution including DNS, networking and DR strategy. The production version involved the building of 30+ servers, installing and configuring base software and deployment of in-house products. Standalone instances were automated for a self-service PaaS which compressed all of the product onto a single VM for dev/test use. This was all managed and controlled using GitFlow and Jenkins for Continuous Integration

- Lead multi-million pound project to refactor and upgrade lucrative legacy system including architecting DNS, Networking and DR strategy
- Implemented Automation strategy saving dozens of man hours per month
- Automated Product deployments for building, upgrading and downgrading like for like environments across Development, Test and Production
- Implemented GitFlow as the de facto standard for automation code management
- Utilised Git/Bitbucket in conjunction with Jenkins for use in CI/CD Pipelines
- Championed HashiCorp Vault for Secret Management and oversaw early implementation
- Oversaw the definition of OLAs and the redefinition of workflows in IT Service Management system
- Set up an offshore DevOps team in Kochi, India as we wound down offices in the UK
- After cancelling Oracle Support, successfully passed a second Oracle Audit fully licensed and compliant

#### **Database Administration Manager**

June 2010 to December 2016

My responsibility expanded from 2 to 20 data centres and to SQL Server for 24-7-365 online gaming

- Solely responsible for availability and performance of all production databases
- Managed hundreds of Oracle and MSSQL databases across 50+ servers in 20 data centres
- Administration of databases processing 2000 transactions per second and up to 9TB is size
- Built and managed Database Development, Oracle DBA and MSSQL DBA teams from scratch
- Project managing out of place upgrades to new hardware and software
- Retrofitting storage, memory and CPU to production systems
- Designed and managing retrofit of data retention solution to large production systems
- Storage architecture and capacity planning for optimal performance and ease
- Process creation, documentation and oversight for Technical Operations Department
- Full responsibility for all Oracle Licensing, internal and external as an ISV
- Successfully passed an Oracle Audit as fully licensed and compliant

#### **Oracle Database Administrator**

September 2008 to June 2010

Initially focused on the database development lifecycle, I became a production DBA leading the team.

- Built RAC clusters with Partitioning on Red Hat Enterprise Linux for Production and Test systems
- Performed Point-In-Time Recovery exercises and Switchover testing using Data Guard
- Performance Tuning using Enterprise Manager with Diagnostics and Tuning, ASH and ASSM
- Created method to produce SQL to recreate target database's DDL for new product installations.

#### **Database Developer**

January 2007 to September 2008

Database developer for both the in-house Oracle platform and distributed SQL Server solutions.

- Introduced database code standards and change management
- Optimising content delivery by User-Defined Aggregate function on generated binary values
- Took on temporary responsibility for SQL Server Reporting Services due to an exodus of staff

# **Touchpaper Software Limited (now LANDESK)**Product Support Analyst Woking, UK February 2004 to January 2007

Touchpaper was an international provider of ITIL based IT Business Management solutions.

- On site consultation for tuning databases and pre-sales as database specialist
- Extensive SQL solutions to remap corrupted product metadata in both Oracle and MS SQL Server
- Developing data migration solutions for out-of-place upgrades

## **Datacraft Design Ltd**

Database Technician

London, UK

February 2000 to February 2004

Datacraft Design was a small company which produced facilities management software.

- Developed PL/SQL and T-SQL for the product suite
- Installed and configured Datacraft's products and then trained administrators and end-users
- Performed pre-sales presentations, once at Barclays Global Investors in New York
- · Consulted at Deutsche Bank, Merrill Lynch, UBS, HSBC and Citigroup among many others
- Customer relationship management with senior personnel culminating in designing the reports used to coordinate and charge for events at Buckingham Palace with the Keeper of the Privy Purse

## **Certifications**

AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner	March 2023
ITIL Foundation Certificate in IT Service Management	February 2023
ICAgile Certified Professional	December 2017
M102: MongoDB for DBAs Completion	April 2014
Oracle 11g Certified Professional	February 2012

# **Education & Training**

Feb 2021	AWS Cloud Practitioner Training		AWS Remote Training
Dec 2017	Agile Fundamentals	L	earning Tree, London, UK
Nov 2017	Introduction to Kubernetes		Google, London, UK
Dec 2016	System and Network Security Introduction	L	earning Tree, London, UK
Oct 2016	Oracle 12c New Features		StayAhead, London, UK
Oct 2015	Developing High-Performance SQL Server Da	tabases L	earning Tree, London, UK
Feb 2014	M102: MongoDB for DBAs		Six Week Online Course
May 2013	Oracle 11g RAC and Grid Infrastructure Admir	nistration Ed	3 Oracle, London, UK
Nov 2009	Oracle Database 11g: RAC Administration Ed	1	Oracle, Reading, UK
Spring 2002	Unix for Users	C	ity University, London, UK
Autumn 1999	Oracle Database Administration	Clarke Univ	ersity, Braintree, MA. USA
1998 – 1999	University of Massachusetts Amherst		Amherst, MA. USA
	Astronomy Major with Senior Standing		Cumulative Average: 3.5

# **Nationality**

Dual Citizen of the USA and Ireland with indefinite leave to remain in the United Kingdom

## **Leisure Interests**

Spending time with my children, woodland walks, fitness and socialising